{"tossups": [{"question": "In this country, a rock garden with sculptures made from recycled waste and a steel sculpture of an open hand are found in sectors of one city. The first Prime Minister of this country commissioned Le Corbusier to design that planned city, Chandigarh. Another monument in this country is named for the colored sandstone it was built with when the capital was moved from Agra. For ten points, name this country where Mughal rulers once used the Peacock Throne in the Red Fort in Delhi.", "answer": "Republic of<b> India</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "This group secured power in Chelmno Land after its natives agreed to the Treaty of Christburg. This group expanded operations in Prussia at the request of Konrad of Masovia. This group failed to take Pskov from Alexander Nevsky after being defeated on Lake Peipus in the Battle of the Ice. The influence of this group declined after losing at Grunwald to Poland-Lithuania. For ten points, name this group of German crusaders.", "answer": "<b> Teutonic Order</b> (or<b> Teutonic Knights</b>; accept<b> Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem</b>) (3) Development along the Tuolumne [to-all-um-nee] River in this state was unsuccessfully opposed by John Muir. The O\u2019Shaughnessy Dam filled up this state\u2019s Hetch Hetchy Valley in 1923. Glacier Point and Vernal Fall are located in a national park in this state on the west side of the Sierra Nevada mountains. Half Dome was photographed numerous times by Ansel Adams in, for ten points, what US state that is home to Yosemite National Park? ANSWER:<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The ban liang coin was standardized under this man\u2019s chancellor Li Si, who forged a letter ordering this man\u2019s son Fusu to commit suicide. This man survived an assassination attempt in which a blind musician struck out at him with a heavy lute. The ascension of this man marked the end of the Warring States period, and he was buried alongside thousands of terracotta warriors. For ten points, name this first emperor of the Qin dynasty.", "answer": "Qin<b> Shi Huang</b>di", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Mary Dyer was hanged in this city, making her one of this city\u2019s three namesake martyrs. In a lawsuit involving this city and its northern suburb, Daniel Webster argued against the Warren Bridge Company in the Charles River Bridge case. A 1773 incident in this city led to the Coercive Acts and began when men boarded the<em> Beaver</em> and other ships dressed as Mohawk Indians. For ten points, name this city where Samuel Adams led a disruptive Tea Party.", "answer": "<b> Boston</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This president rejected Texas\u2019 first application for annexation. This politician led the Albany Regency, a group of New York politicians, and his supposedly lavish lifestyle in the White House was attacked by Charles Ogle in the Gold Spoon Oration. This man ordered Winfield Scott to carry out his predecessor\u2019s Indian Removal Act, causing the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this US president who succeeded Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "Martin<b> Van Buren</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This discipline\u2019s focus was shifted onto social constructions, rather than observables, by Giambattista Vico\u2019s<em> verum factum</em> principle. The \u201cheroic\u201d in this discipline was discussed by Thomas Carlyle, who developed a \u201cGreat Man\u201d theory of it. Authors in this field\u2019s Dunning School promoted a \u201clost cause\u201dnarrative of the Confederacy in school textbooks. For ten points, name this study of humanity\u2019s past.", "answer": "<b> history</b> (accept more descriptive answers, such as \u201cthe philosophy of<b> history</b>\u201d; do not accept philosophy alone; do not acept historiography)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "The beginning of this event was signalled with the phrase, \u201ccrack the sky, shake the Earth,\u201d and it continued in the May Offensive. One theory suggests the Battle of Khe Sanh was a diversion for this event, in which blacklisted civilians were buried alive in Hue [Hway]. This operation led to the infiltration of the U.S. embassy in Saigon by Viet Cong guerillas. The breaking of the Lunar New Year truce started, for ten points, what 1968 offensive that caused U.S. public opinion to turn against the Vietnam War?", "answer": "<b> Tet</b> Offensive", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 2010, nine activists trying to bring aid to this territory were killed when their \u201cFreedom Flotilla\u201dwas raided. This region\u2019s southwest border lies on the narrow Philadelphia Corridor, which is patrolled by an Egyptian Border Guard Force. In 2005, all Israeli settlements in this region were vacated, as were four in the West Bank. For ten points, name this self-governing Palestinian territory, a strip along the Mediterranean Sea.", "answer": "<b> Gaza</b> Strip (prompt on Palestine)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The towns of Hastings and Rye received tax exemptions in exchange for maintaining these objects as part of a group of five protected cities. Sutton Hoo is the site of a buried, undisturbed one of these objects from the 7th century. Henry I\u2019s son William Adelin was killed in a disaster involving one of these vehicles, which were used during raids on English monasteries. For ten points, name these vehicles built in Southampton and other English port cities.", "answer": "<b> ship</b>s (accept<b> boat</b>s; accept<b> longship</b> after Sutton Hoo is said) Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician attacked his opponent\u2019s support for weekend furlough passes in the Willie Horton ad. In another ad, this man listed his opponent\u2019s opposition to military bills while his opponent rode in a tank. This man called trickle-down economics \u201cvoodoo economics\u201d before serving as Ronald Reagan\u2019s Vice President. For ten points, name this man who reneged on his promise of \u201cno new taxes,\u201d then lost his re-election campaign to Bill Clinton in 1992.", "answer": "George<b> H</b>erbert<b> W</b>alker<b> Bush</b> (accept<b> Bush the Elder</b> or<b> Bush</b> the<b> 41</b>st; prompt on (George) Bush; do not accept \u201cGeorge Walker Bush\u201d or other references to his son; do not accept George Bush Sr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this dynasty, the heqin [huh-CHEEN] system of using marriages for peace was used to repel an attack by Xiongnu [shong-nu] Emperor Modu Chanyu. Sima Qian [see-ma chee-ahn] wrote the<em> Records</em> <em>of the Grand Historian</em> during the reign of this dynasty\u2019s Emperor Wu. The Trung Sisters attempted to liberate Vietnam from this dynasty, which was founded by Liu Bang. For ten points, name this dynasty that shares its name with China\u2019s largest ethnic group.", "answer": "<b> Han</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "According to myth, this nation was created by two gods named \u201cHe-who-invites\u201d and \u201cShe-who-is-invited\u201d and the help of a giant spear. This country is the birthplace of a religion that uses purification rituals called<em> harae</em> [ha-rah-ay] and whose holiest shrine is rebuilt every 20 years. In 1995, a doomsday cult carried out a sarin attack in this nation\u2019s largest city. The Ise [ee-say] and Yasukuni shrines can be found in, for ten points, what Asian country where Shinto developed in the 8th century and is practiced in Tokyo?", "answer": "<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, the term \u201ckhaki election,\u201d was coined to describe an election influenced by an ongoing or finished war. The Fawcett Commission was formed after Emily Hobhouse reported on concentration camps used in this war. Prior to this war, Cecil Rhodes sponsored a failed attempt to trigger a settler uprising, the Jameson Raid. The British established control over the Orange Free State and the Transvaal in, for ten points, what South African war named for the defeated Dutch settlers?", "answer": "Second<b> Boer</b> War (or the Anglo-<b>Boer</b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man authorized military intervention against Samos after Miletus asked for aid in a war for the city of Priene. This man secured power over his rivals, Cimon and Thucydides, through ostracism. This man described the greatness of his city in a celebrated funeral oration and hired Iktinos and Kallikrates to renovate the Acropolis. For ten points, name this leader of the Delian League and statesman of Athens during its Golden Age.", "answer": "<b> Pericles</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this city, a white monument smeared by black paint was relocated into St. John\u2019s Cemetery after its removal from Dalhousie Square. A tragedy in this city was recounted in the writings of J.Z. Howell, who noted that nobody dared to wake the Nawab of Bengal. This city was the site of Fort William, whose troops were captured in 1756 and crammed into a tiny space. Over one hundred British soldiers were suffocated to death in, for ten points, what east Indian city\u2019s \u201cBlack Hole?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Calcutta</b> (or<b> Kolkata</b>; accept Black Hole of<b> Calcutta</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During his time as governor of Africa, this man was pelted by turnips and found himself in financial difficulty, causing him to turn to the mule trade. This man fell out of imperial</b> <b>favor after falling asleep during one of (+)</b> <b>Nero\u2019s lyre recitals. During the Great Jewish</b> <b>Revolt, this man threw captured prisoners into the Dead Sea to test its legendary buoyancy; that revolt was later crushed by his son (*)</b> Titus. For ten points, name this founder of the Flavian dynasty, the last Emperor during the Year of the Four Emperors.", "answer": "<b> Vespasian</b> (or Titus Flavius Caesar<b> Vespasian</b>us Augustus, but do not accept or prompt any of the individual names alone)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1967, this man argued that \u201cit\u2019s [the media\u2019s] responsibility for spreading\u201d the news that he had taken LSD, denying he had \u201cencouraged\u201d his fans to take drugs. This man was</b> <b>arrested in Tokyo for possession of marijuana in 1980, canceling a (+)</b> <b>Wings tour and</b> <b>ultimately causing the breakup of the band. Drug-inspired songs like \u201cGot to Get You Into My Life,\u201d and \u201cMagical (*) </b> Mystery Tour\u201d were sung by, for ten points, what British singer who co-wrote those songs with John Lennon in The Beatles?", "answer": "(James) Paul<b> McCartney</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Prince Johnson videotaped the torture of this country\u2019s President Samuel Doe to prove he was not protected by black magic. Two women from this country and one from Yemen shared the 2011 (+) Nobel Peace Prize; one of those women, Ellen Johnson Sirleaf, opposed</b> <b>warlord Charles (*)</b> Taylor, who was convicted of crimes against humanity for this country\u2019s 20th century civil wars. For ten points, name this African country whose capital, Monrovia, was founded by the American Colonization Society as a home for freed slaves.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Liberia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One composer from this country wrote a ballet about the Roman slave leader</b><em><b> Spartacus </b></em><b>and another work, set on a</b><em><b> kolkhoz</b></em><b>, that is known for a xylophone solo. The Mariinsky</b> <b>Ballet was renamed the (+)</b> <b>Kirov Ballet in this country, where Aram Khachaturian\u2019s</b> <em><b>Gayane</b></em><b> included the \u201cSabre Dance.\u201d In 1961, a dancer from this country became the first artist to (*)</b> defect during the Cold War. Rudolf Nureyev and Mikhail Baryshnikov were from, for ten points, what country where artists were awarded the Stalin Prize?", "answer": "<b> Soviet Union</b> (accept<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b> or<b> USSR</b> or<b> CCCP</b> or <b>SSSR</b>; prompt on Armenia before \u201cMariinsky\u201d is read; do not accept Russia)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {"question": "<b>This battle was the subject of the</b><em><b> Gesta Henrici Quinti</b></em><b>, a propaganda piece that has made historians question whether a baggage train was attacked at the beginning or end of this battle. (+) Stakes and muddy ground hampered the effectiveness of one side\u2019s cavalry in this battle which, like the Battle of (*)</b> Crecy 70 years earlier, reaffirmed the superiority of the longbow. For ten points, name this 1415 battle of the Hundred Years\u2019 War, a victory for England on Saint Crispin\u2019s Day.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Agincourt</b> ", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This city was the site of a far-right National Front march that burst into violence</b> <b>during the Battle of Lewisham. In this city\u2019s Battle of Cable Street, Oswald Mosley\u2019s</b> <b>Fascists clashed with counter-protesters in the (+)</b> <b>East End. Every World War II</b> <b>Allied government-in-exile except Denmark relocated to this capital city, which was</b> <b>the target of the abandoned Operation (*)</b> Sea Lion. For ten points, name this capital city that was protected from Luftwaffe bombings by the Royal Air Force during \u201cthe Blitz.\u201d", "answer": "<b> London</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}